OLALLA DÍAZ-YÁÑEZ

University of Eastern Finland P.O. 111. School of Forest Sciences 80101 Joensuu, Finland. +358 40 8269912

> olalla.diaz@uef.fi / olalla.diaz@gmail.com www.olalladiaz.net

Researcher, teacher and project manager with research experience in forest stand dynamics, forest ecology, forest management and natural disturbances. Creative, problem solver, team-oriented with good communication skills, results-driven with talents in science communication, planning and organisation. Extensive international experience having worked in organisations such as IUFRO HQ, US Forest Service, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, University of Eastern Finland and Polytechnic University of Madrid. Qualifications include:

- Scientific programming and simulation with R •
- Data management and visualisation
- Personal organisation
- Time management

- Communication
- Flexibility
- Leadership
- Pedagogical competence

Language

English (full professional proficiency). Spanish (native). French, Swedish & Finnish (basic).

Education

PhD (Expected defence summer 2018) — University of Eastern Finland, Joensuu, Finland MSc Forest Management, 2013 — Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Umeå, Sweden MSc European Forestry, 2013 — University of Eastern Finland, Joensuu, Finland B.E. Forest Engineering, 2011 — Technical University of Madrid, Madrid, Spain

Appointments Researcher, School of Forest Sciences. University of Eastern Finland 2014-Present

Visiting researcher, University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences (BOKU) Vienna, Austria 2018 Visiting researcher, US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station April-August, 2017

Visiting teacher, University of Vigo, Pontevedra, Spain 2016

Visiting researcher, CTFC, Solsona, Spain 2016 Visiting researcher, NIBIO, Ås, Norway 2015 Visiting researcher, CTFC, Solsona, Spain 2014

Experience

Early Stage Researcher, University of Eastern Finland; Joensuu, Finland — 2014-now My PhD research relates forest risk from natural disturbances with stand dynamics and forest management. I have modelled natural disturbances in Norway based on 20 years National Forest Inventory data (about 80.000 observations). I have also developed a stand dynamic simulator and an optimisation algorithm to find forest management recommendations that consider snow and wind damages, evaluate biodiversity, carbon capture and forest development.

Researcher, US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station April-August 2017 During my visit I collaborated with the Resource Monitoring and Assessment team. I used the Forest Inventory data on the west cost of the US to predict the snag standing survival after a fire damage on natural reserves. The main objective was to find out the real value of the snags as habitat and carbon storage.

Project Assistant, IUFRO; Vienna, Austria — (short term) 2012

Assist in the development of the project EcoAdapt and its founding program FORNESSA. Participate in the selection process of founded applicants and write a scientific report.

Research Assistant, University of Eastern Finland; Joensuu, Finland — 2011-2012 Project related to bioenergy, plantations and governance.

Teacher, FESSA (Social Studies Foundation in the Agricultural and Food Sector); Madrid,

Spain - 2011

Teacher, course coordinator on forestry oriented courses for forestry professionals.

Researcher, METLA (Finnish Forest Research Institute); Joensuu, Finland — 2009-2010

Investigate constraints for wood procurement in selected EU countries.

Teaching Over 3 years as a teaching assistant and leader, with experience designing curriculum,

developing new teaching tools, grading, overseeing labs and guest lecturing. Courses include: data science with R, statistical research methods, academic skills, biomass for energy, forest

management and planning.

Supervision Co-supervision of two MSc thesis

Funding / Grants

10.000€ Marie Curie - RISE under the project SuFoRun (2017) 2000€ European Forest Institute Short Scientific Visits (2017)

300€ Conference fee grant - Grant of the Finnish Society of Forest Science (2017)

800€ Conference travel grant - University of Eastern Finland (2017)

2260€ Short Term Scientific Mission-Reference COST Action FP1206 (2016)

500€ Organise activities for the Doctoral Association - University of Eastern Finland (2016)

Service / Leadership

Vice-member in the School of Forest Sciences (UEF) steering committee 2018-Vice-chair of the University of Eastern Finland Doctoral Student Association 2016-17 Board member of the University of Eastern Finland Doctoral Student Association 2014-17

Board representative in the FORES Doctoral school program 2016-

Board representative in the NOVA network (Nordic Forestry, Veterinary and Agricultural

University Network: Denmark, Norway, Finland & Sweden) 2017

Secretary non-profit organisation Edusilva 2015-16

Outreach PhD mentoring program University of Eastern Finland 2016-17

Coding in school- Teaching code to 4th grade school students

Cultural volunteering - Immigration inclusion, developing leisure programs for children 2015-17

Awards / Recognition

Recognition of high quality review in Forestry: An international Journal of Forest Research (2018)

Appointments Editorial board of Forestry: An international Journal of Forest Research (2018)

for scientific Reviewer in Forestry: An international Journal of Forest Research

journals

References Prof. Timo Pukkala

Faculty of Natural Sciences and Forestry. University of Eastern Finland, Joensuu campus PL 111 (Yliopistokatu 7), 80101 Joensuu p. 050 4423 372, email: timo.pukkala@uef.fi

Senior Researcher Vicente Monleon

USDA Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station. Resource Monitoring and Assessment. 3200 SW Jefferson Way, Corvallis, Oregon, United States. p. 97331-8550, email: vjmonleon@fs.fed.us

University Researcher Blas Mola-Yudego

Faculty of Natural Sciences and Forestry. University of Eastern Finland, Joensuu campus PL 111 (Yliopistokatu 7), 80101 Joensuu p. 050 4422974, email: blas.mola@uef.fi

Publications

Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B. & González-Olabarria, J.R., Pukkala, T., 2017. How does forest composition and structure affect the stability against wind and snow? Forest Ecology and Management, 401, pp. 215–222, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2017.06.054

Mola-Yudego, B., Arevalo J., **Díaz-Yáñez**, **O.** et al. 2017. Wood biomass potentials for energy in northern Europe: Forest or plantations?, Biomass and Bioenergy, https://doi.org/10.1016/ j.biombioe.2017.08.021

Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B. & González-Olabarria, J.R., 2017. What variables make a forest stand vulnerable to browsing damage occurrence? Silva Fennica, 51(2), pp.1-11. https://doi.org/ 10.14214/sf.1693

Mola-Yudego, B., Arevalo, J., Díaz-Yáñez, O., Dimitriou, I., Freshwater, E., Haapala, A., Khanam, T. and Selkimäki, M. 2017. Reviewing wood biomass potentials for energy in Europe: the role of forests and fast growing plantations, Biofuels, https://doi.org/10.1080/17597269.2016.1271627

Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B., Eriksen, R. and González-Olabarria, J.R. 2016. Assessment of the Main Natural Disturbances on Norwegian Forest Based on 20 Years of National Inventory. PloS one, 11(8), https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0161361

Mola-Yudego, B., Díaz-Yáñez, O. and Dimitriou, I., 2015. How Much Yield Should We Expect from Fast-Growing Plantations for Energy? Divergences Between Experiments and Commercial Willow Plantations. BioEnergy Research, 8(4), pp.1769-1777. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12155-015-9630-1

Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B., Anttila, P., Röser, D. and Asikainen, A., 2013. Forest chips for energy in Europe: Current procurement methods and potentials. Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews, 21, pp.562-571. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rser.2012.12.016

In review

Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B., González-Olabarria, J. R. 2018. Modelling and mapping occurrence of wind and snow forest damage. European Journal of Forest Research.

Díaz-Yáñez. O., Arias-Rodil, M., Mola-Yudego, B., González-Olabarria, J. R., Pukkala, T. 2018. Effects of wind and snow damage on the optimal management of Norwegian spruce forests. Forestry: An International Journal of Forest Research

Presentations Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B. & González-Olabarria, J.R., Pukkala, T. Forest stand variables affecting break and uproot of trees after the occurrence of wind and snow damage. Ecological Society of America Annual Meeting. Portland, Oregon, United States. August 6-11, 2017

Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B. & González-Olabarria, J.R., Pukkala, T. What makes a forest stand more vulnerable to snow and wind damage? 8th International Conference on Wind and Trees. Boulder, Colorado, United States. July 17-21, 2017.

Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B. & González-Olabarria, J.R. What variables make a young forest stand more vulnerable to ungulate browsing occurrence? Conference: Forest Regeneration -IUFRO. Corvallis, Oregon, United States. Jul 11-13, 2017

Díaz-Yáñez, O., Mola-Yudego, B. Ash mortality curves in Norway. Resipath. Burdeaux, France. December 2016.